<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect1 id="zendx.console.process.unix.overview">
    <title>ZendX_Console_Process_Unix</title>

    <sect2 id="zendx.console.process.unix.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            <classname>ZendX_Console_Process_Unix</classname> allows developers to spawn
            an object as a new process, and so do multiple tasks in parallel on
            console environments. Through its specific nature, it is only
            working on *nix based systems like Linux, Solaris, Mac/OSx and such.
            Additionally, the <code>shmop_*</code>, <code>pcntl_*</code> and
            <code>posix_*</code> modules are required for this component to
            run. If one of the requirements is not met, it will throw an
            exception after instantiating the component.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zendx.console.process.unix.basic">
        <title>Basic usage of ZendX_Console_Process_Unix</title>
        <para>
            <classname>ZendX_Console_Process_Unix</classname> is an abstract class, which
            requires the user to extend it. It has a single abstract method
            called <methodname>_run()</methodname> which has to be implemented to create a
            working process. It also comes with multiple methods for checking
            the alive status and share variables between the parent and the
            child process.
        </para>

        <para>
            The <methodname>_run()</methodname> method and every method which is called
            by it is executed by the child process. Every other method which is
            called directly by the parent is executed by the parent process.
        </para>

        <para>
            <methodname>setVariable()</methodname> and <methodname>getVariable()</methodname> can be
            used from both the parent- and the child process to share variables.
            To observe the alive status, the child process should call
            <methodname>_setAlive()</methodname> in a frequent interval, so that the parent
            process can check the last alive time via <methodname>getLastAlive()</methodname>.
            To get the PID of the child process, the parent can call
            <methodname>getPid()</methodname>.
        </para>

        <example id="zendx.console.process.unix.example">
            <title>Basic example for processing</title>
            <para>
                This example illustrates a basic child process
            </para>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
class MyProcess extends ZendX_Console_Process_Unix
{
    protected function _run()
    {
        for ($i = 0; $i < 10; $i++) {
            // Doing something really important which can't wait: sleeping
            sleep(1);
        }
    }
}

// This part should last about 10 seconds, not 20.
$process1 = new MyProcess();
$process1->start();

$process2 = new MyProcess();
$process2->start();

while ($process1->isRunning() || $process2->isRunning()) {
    sleep(1);
}

echo 'All processes completed';
]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                In this example a process is forked twice and executed. As every
                process runs 10 seconds, the parent process will be finished after
                10 seconds (and not 20).
            </para>
        </example>

    </sect2>
</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
